Inventory of Education and World Affairs records, 1961-1971
Hoover Institution Archives
Education and World Affairs records
1951-1973
2015C17
Hoover Institution Archives
18 manuscript boxes (7.51 linear feet)
Governing documents, minutes, correspondence, memoranda, reports, and printed matter relating to international education from Education and World Affairs, a private American nonprofit organization created in 1962 for the promotion of internationalism in education. Education and World Affairs is the predecessor of the International Council for Educational Development.
Education and World Affairs.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2015.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical note
Education and World Affairs was a private American nonprofit organization created in 1962 to study, analyze, and assist in strengthening the international teaching, research, and service dimensions of colleges and universities in the United States. The organization is the predecessor of the International Council for Educational Development.
Scope and Content of Collection
Governing documents, minutes, correspondence, memoranda, reports, and printed matter relating to international education from Education and World Affairs, a private American nonprofit organization created in 1962 for the promotion of internationalism in education. Education and World Affairs is the predecessor of the International Council for Educational Development.
Education--United States.; International education.
- Institutional Materials, 1961-1971 (Box 1-16)
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence, records, memoranda, notes, proposals, and meeting minutes from Education and World Affairs.
  - "The Princeton University Conference on Foreign Language and Area Studies in the United States: A Guide for High School and College Programs, December 17-18, 1965," reprint from The Educational Record, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Report from Education and World Affairs to the Carnegie Corporation of New York, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Certification of incorporation, undated (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - By-laws of Education and World Affairs, 1970 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Miscellaneous memoranda and notes, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - "The Quasi Nongovernmental Organization," Alan Pifer, 1967 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Miscellaneous clippings and notes, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Merger and transition files, 1970 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Notes and memoranda regarding institutional history, 1966-1968 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Conference materials from the North East conference on Higher Education and the Two Year College and International Education conference, 1970 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Memoranda regarding budgets of federal agencies, 1971 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Program planning, 1969-1971 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - International Council for Educational Development materials, 1970 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Drafts of memoranda, 1967 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Staff papers, 1970 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - General international education materials, 1965-1968 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - William W. Marvel, 1970 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - "U.S. Owned Foreign Currencies," article reprint, 1964 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - "Why International Education?," Gerard J. Mangone, 1970 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Study on Overseas Academic Placement, 1968 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Planning materials, 1966 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Robert Leestman, 1969 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Early institutional materials, 1962 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Project Vacuum, 1970 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Miscellaneous memoranda, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 3: 6-7)
  - Education and World Affairs staff manual, 1966 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Documentation for the Meeting of the Committee on Educational Interchange Policy, 1963 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - "Education for Social Change,", 1961 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - "A Crisis of Dollars: The Funding Threat to International Affairs in U.S. Higher Education," report, 1969 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - "New Patterns for 1969: A Report on Overseas Academic Placement," (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - International reports regarding education, undated (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Correspondence to William Marvel, including Marvel's curriculum vitae, 1969-1971 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Memoranda, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Institutional reports, 1964-1968 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - "Nigerian Human Resource Development and Utilization," report from Education and World Affairs, 1967 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Miscellaneous institutional records, 1962-1970 (Box-folder 5: 1-2)
  - Education and World Affairs Washington Log, Volume 2, Number 4, 1970 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Notes on Senate bill 2874 and House Resolution 14643, 1966 (Box-folder 5: 4)
    "International Education Act Hearings Before the Subcommittee on Education of the Committee on Labor and Public Welfare United States Senate."
  - "A New Agency in the Field of Education and World Affairs," report of Task Force to the Carnegie Corporation, the Rockefeller Foundation, and the Ford Foundation, 1961 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Dean Rusk Committee report, 1968 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Study on Overseas Academic Placement, 1968 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - Agnelli Foundation, Turin, Italy, undated (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - William Marvel personal material, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - Proposal to Ford Foundation, 1965 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - John B. Howard, 1966 (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - Proposal to the Carnegie Corporation, 1967 (Box-folder 5: 12-13)
  - Proposal to the Carnegie Corporation, draft, 1966 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Correspondence, 1969 September (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - Education and World Affairs Trustees' profiles, 1969 (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - Excerpts from Board of Trustees discussion with Douglass Cater and Francis Keppel, 1965 (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - Memoranda from William Marvel, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - International Education Act, 1966 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - Testimony before the Task Force on International Education, 1966 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - Hearings on the International Education Act, 1966 (Box-folder 6: 8)
  - Operation Smithsonian material, 1965 (Box-folder 7: 1-3)
  - Smithsonian Task Force Report, undated (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - Materials regarding the International Education Act, 1967 (Box-folder 7: 5)
  - William Marvel's statement before the Subcommittee on Government Research, 1966 (Box-folder 7: 6)
  - Correspondence to William Marvel regarding Task Force on International Education, undated (Box-folder 7: 7)
  - Memorandum regarding "Organizing the planning and consultation with the academic community required by the International Education Act,", 1966 (Box-folder 7: 8)
  - Memorandum regarding "Education and South Vietnam: A new dimension for President Johnson's 'peace offensive,'", 1965 (Box-folder 7: 9)
  - Excerpt from memorandum regarding South Vietnam, 1965 (Box-folder 7: 10)
  - Memorandum regarding Vietnam and board meetings, 1967 (Box-folder 7: 11)
  - Notes prepared for Trustees, 1967 (Box-folder 7: 12)
  - Notes on meeting of Trustees at the White House, 1967 (Box-folder 7: 13)
  - Memorandum to Board of Trustees regarding South Vietnam, 1967 (Box-folder 7: 14)
  - Documents prepared for Trustees, 1967 (Box-folder 7: 15)
  - Vietnam materials, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Annual report, 1967 (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - Membership invitations to join Committee on International Studies, 1967 (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - Committee on International Studies, 1967 (Box-folder 8: 4)
  - International Studies Seminar, 1968 (Box-folder 8: 5)
  - Crisis in funding study, 1967 (Box-folder 8: 6)
  - "A New Instrumentality for Government Financing of Private International Activities in Education and Related Areas,", 1967 (Box-folder 8: 7)
  - "Study Plan: Design of New Government Foundation,", undated (Box-folder 8: 8)
  - Memorandum regarding the Rusk Committee, 1967 (Box-folder 8: 9)
  - Memorandum regarding the "Report on a New Instrumentality for Government Financing of Private International Activities in Education and Related Areas,", 1967 (Box-folder 8: 10)
  - International migration of talent, 1967 (Box-folder 8: 11)
  - Program directions and priorities, 1965 (Box-folder 8: 12)
  - Board of Trustees' memoranda, 1966 (Box-folder 8: 13)
  - Business council, 1966 (Box-folder 8: 14)
  - Report to the directors of the Adlai E. Stevenson Memorial Fund, 1966 (Box-folder 8: 15)
  - "Federal Programs in Education Designed to Improve International Understanding and Cooperation," final report, 1969 (Box-folder 8: 16)
  - Speeches, 1964-1969 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - "A Comparative Approach to the Study of Foreign Policy: Notes on Theorizing," Edward L. Morse, 1971 (Box-folder 9: 2)
  - Future of Education and World Affairs in Africa, 1970 (Box-folder 9: 3)
  - Articles and speeches by William W. Marvel, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 9: 4-6)
  - Memoranda, meeting minutes, and notes, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 9: 7)
  - Saturday Review, 1966 (Box-folder 9: 8)
  - Trustees' meeting, 1968 (Box-folder 9: 9)
  - Proposal to Ford Foundation, 1969 (Box-folder 9: 10)
  - Proposal to US Aid, 1969 (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - Memoranda, meeting minutes, and press releases, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 10: 2-3)
  - Institutional memoranda and lease agreement, 1965-1970 (Box-folder 10: 4)
  - International Council for Educational Development materials, 1970 (Box-folder 10: 5)
  - Memoranda, correspondence, and proposals, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 10: 6-7)
  - Memoranda, 1970 (Box-folder 10: 8)
  - Report and paper, 1970 (Box-folder 10: 9)
  - Intercambios, 1966 (Box-folder 10: 10)
  - Memoranda, 1966-1970 (Box-folder 10: 11)
  - Memoranda, 1966-1970 (Box-folder 11: 1-2)
  - Chronological file, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 11: 3-14)
  - Chronological file, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 12: 1-9)
  - Board of Trustees' meeting minutes, 1962-1966 (Box-folder 12: 10-14)
  - Board of Trustees' meeting minutes, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 13: 1-4)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1969 (Box-folder 13: 5)
  - Planning materials, 1968 (Box-folder 13: 6)
  - Language and area studies, 1972 (Box-folder 13: 7)
  - International program and proposals, 1958-1960 (Box-folder 13: 8)
  - Institutional flow chart, undated (Box-folder 13: 9)
  - Report, 1961 (Box-folder 14: 1)
  - The Professional School and World Affairs Newsletter, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 14: 2)
  - "International Education: America's Hottest Cargo,", 1967 (Box-folder 14: 3)
  - "Intercultural Studies,", 1967 (Box-folder 14: 4)
  - "International Education,", 1969 (Box-folder 14: 5)
  - "The College and World Affairs,", circa 1960s (Box-folder 14: 6)
  - World Studies Data Bank Report on International Education, 1972 (Box-folder 14: 7)
  - Articles by Jacob Viner, 1951 (Box-folder 14: 8)
  - "The Pole of Power and the Pole of Indifference," Arnold Wolfer, 1951 (Box-folder 14: 9)
  - "Twenty Years in Retrospect: A Personal View," Alan Pifer, 1973 (Box-folder 14: 10)
  - Phi Delta Kappan, 1967-1970 (Box-folder 14: 11)
  - Intercultural Education, Volumes 1 and 2, 1969-1971 (Box-folder 14: 12-14)
  - Liberal Education, 1963 (Box-folder 15: 1)
  - Background, Journal of the International Studies Association, 1965 (Box-folder 15: 2)
  - Vidya, Vidya, Vidya, 1967 (Box-folder 15: 3)
  - New Prospects for the Small Liberal Arts College, Sidney S. Letter, 1968 (Box-folder 15: 4)
  - "A NATO Nuclear Force: The Problem of Management," Klaus Knorr, 1963 (Box-folder 15: 5)
  - "International Council for Educational Development Data Bank on International Programs of Higher Educational Institutions," report, 1971 (Box-folder 15: 6)
  - "The International Role of the University in the 1970s," conference proceedings, 1973 (Box-folder 15: 7)
  - Diversity and Interdependence Through International Education, 1967 (Box-folder 15: 8)
  - The Provincial Universities of Mexico: An Analysis of Growth and Development, Richard G. King, Alfonso Rangel Guerra, David Kline, and Noel F. McGinn, 1971 (Box-folder 15: 9)
  - The International Migration of High-Level Manpower: Its Impact on the Development Process, 1970 (Box-folder 16: 1)
- Publications, 1963-1970 (Box 16-18)
  Materials published by Education and World Affairs.
  - "Overseas Educational Service," pamphlets, 1963 (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - Pamphlets and memoranda, 1967 (Box-folder 16: 3)
  - International Education Act of 1966 (Box-folder 16: 4)
  - "Higher Education and World Affairs," Allan A. Michie, 1968 (Box-folder 16: 5)
  - "Guidelines for the Planning of External Aid Projects in Education," Arthur J. Lewis, 1967 (Box-folder 16: 6)
  - "Scientific Engineering and Technical Education in Mexico," Russell G. Davis, 1967 (Box-folder 16: 7)
  - "Educational Development in Africa: The Role of United States Assistance," John W. Masland, 1967 (Box-folder 16: 8)
  - "United States University Activity Abroad: Implications of the Mexican Case," Charles Nash Myers, 1968 (Box-folder 16: 9)
  - "Problems of Professional Identity: An Examination of Training for Human Resource Development and Educational Planning," Adam Curle, 1968 (Box-folder 16: 10)
  - "Professional Education for World Responsibility," Irwin T. Sanders, 1968 (Box-folder 16: 11)
  - "Inter-Institutional Cooperation and International Education," Sherman L. Witman, 1969 (Box-folder 16: 12)
  - "Internationalizing the U.S. Professional School,", 1969 (Box-folder 17: 1)
  - "U.S. Universities: Their Role in Aid Financed Technical Assistance Overseas," Richard H. Wood, 1968 (Box-folder 17: 2)
  - "Education and World Affairs Report on Program, 1963-1964,", 1965 (Box-folder 17: 3)
  - "The United States Office of Education: A New International Dimension,", 1964 (Box-folder 17: 4)
  - "The Overseas Selection of Foreign Students,", 1966 (Box-folder 17: 5)
  - "Education and World Affairs: An Overview,", 1966 (Box-folder 17: 6)
  - "Brain Drain or Overflow?," George B. Baldwin, 1970 (Box-folder 17: 7)
  - "International Offices on United States and Canadian Campuses: A Directory,", 1967-1970 (Box-folder 17: 8)
  - "International Offices on United States Campuses: A Directory,", 1969 (Box-folder 17: 9)
  - "Coordinating International Programs and Activities at U.S. Colleges and Universities: A Directory,", 1966 (Box-folder 17: 10)
  - "Responsibilities of the Foreign Scholar to the Local Scholarly Community: Studies of the U.S. Research in Guatemala, Chile, and Paraguay," Calvin P. Blair, Richard P. Schaedel, and James H. Street, 1969 (Box-folder 17: 11)
  - "Selected Publications and Research Related to the International Migration of Professional Manpower,", 1968 (Box-folder 17: 12)
  - "The Technology of Instruction in Mexican Universities," Noel F. McGinn, Russell G. Davis, and Richard G. King, 1968 (Box-folder 17: 13)
  - The College and World Affairs, 1964 (Box-folder 17: 14)
  - The University and World Affairs, 1960 (Box-folder 17: 15)
  - The Professional School and World Affairs, 1967 (Box-folder 18: 1-2)
  - Diversity and Interdependence Through International Education, edited by Allan A. Michie, 1967 (Box-folder 18: 3)
  - The Professional School and World Affairs, 1967 (Box-folder 18: 4)